what is equity
have you ever wondered the answer to
that question what is it perhaps in a
conversation you heard someone say yeah
man i have a 150k in equity
what does that even
mean well in this video we're going to
talk about that
so let's say you decide to buy a house
for 300 000
now we're going to keep this discussion
simple we're not going to go into all of
the the details and the fees of owning a
home but let's say that's the current
value of your home
and you took out a loan or mortgage for
three hundred thousand to buy the home
equity
is the difference
between
assets
and liabilities
your home is an asset because
you can go to the market and sell it in
exchange for cash it has a value
the loan is a liability because it's
something you have to pay back
so right now your equity is zero
because these two are the same
but let's say in five years
the value of your home appreciates
to four hundred thousand
so that means that you've gained a
hundred thousand dollars
in appreciation or in value
now in the course of those five years
let's say that you pay down the mortgage
from three hundred thousand
to two hundred ten thousand
how much equity do you now have in your
home
as was mentioned before
equity
is the difference between assets and
liabilities
you have an asset that is four hundred
thousand dollars in value
your liability is two hundred ten
thousand
equity will be the difference between
those two values
so four hundred thousand minus two
hundred ten thousand
will give us
an equity of a hundred ninety thousand
so that's how much equity you would have
in your home so what does that even mean
well it means that if you liquidate your
asset if you sell your home for four
hundred thousand
and
pay all of your mortgage for two hundred
ten thousand
this is how much cash you're going to
have
at the end of those transactions
so equity tells you how much value you
have in your home after paying off all
of your liabilities
that's the basic concept of it so
hopefully this video helped you to
understand the concept of equity as it
relates to your home